[Music]
Hey, what's up guys? My name is Aerno.
Welcome back to another
video. Got my coffee means I can make a
video now. So, today I thought I would
kind of just make a little video. It's
going to be a small one. Kind of a
midweek thing for you guys where I just
I just wanted to talk about something
that I didn't feel would take that long.
That being said, the amount of videos
that I've started off being like this is
going to be a short video and then it's
ended up being something that's like
half an hour long has been like I mean
all of them really. But today we're just
going to talk about the way that I set
up my C++ projects. These aren't
necessarily going to be the best
settings for everyone ever. However, it
is what I use. It's what I've kind of
learned like grown into using over the
years. And honestly, every single C++
project or like and I'm not just talking
about a single project. I'm talking
about like a whole solution of projects.
For every single one that I create from
now on, pretty much I use these
settings. So, let's just let's just jump
in and take a look. So, we've just
opened Visual Studio. We've got our
start page here. Nothing's I haven't
opened any kind of solution yet. I'm
going to create a brand new project and
solution here by hitting file, new, and
then project. For now, I'm just going to
go under Visual C++ General and create
an empty project. And then I'll just
call it something like new project. Now,
in terms of the location, I like to
store the projects that I develop under
the C directory and not inside the user
folder. That way, when I'm switching
computers or anything like that, it's
not going to break any paths. And
really, it's just a lot easier to kind
of store your development projects in
some kind of central directory. So, I
like to do something like C/dev and then
maybe we'll call it new project or
something like that. Now, because we've
got create directory for solution, it
will actually automatically create that
new project folder. So, I don't need to
write that. I'll just hit okay and we'll
see what happens.
I'm sure it's taking a while. Okay, so
once we've got this new empty project,
you can see we have absolutely no files
here or anything like that. If I right
click on the actual project and hit open
folder in file explorer, you'll see the
actual directory structure that Visual
Studio has created for us. So what we've
actually got is inside that dev folder,
we've got that new project. We've got a
solution file right next to there. You
can see that also what Visual Studio has
done is it's called our solution the
exact same name as our project. So
that's not necessarily something that
you want. If this is just going to be a
solution with a single project in it,
then maybe it is. But, you know, if
we're making like a game or something,
then it's very it's very rare for us to
kind of want our solution and project
name to be identical. But anyway, this
structure is actually not bad. Um, we've
got a folder dedicated for our for our
project. We've got both a VCX project
file and a filters file. I'm not going
to get too ind depth about all the
different files Visual Studio creates.
That might be an idea for another video,
but basically the VCX project is our
project file, which is just an XML file.
And then we've also got a solution file,
which is its own kind of weird format.
It's a text file, though. Um, and that's
in its own kind of directory. Okay,
cool. I actually like this structure.
I'm not going to change it too much, but
you'll notice that also what we get here
is a bunch of various folders. Now,
these are not folders, right? These are
things called filters. Filters are not
folders. If I right click on new project
here and do add, you'll see there's no
new folder. It says new filter. And if I
add a filter called churno or something,
nothing is going to change on our disc.
That's not the way that it works. This
filters file, however, does contain
these kind of virtual folders that we
create. So these are fantastic for just
organizing your source code within
folders that don't actually exist on
disk, but they do exist in this solution
explorer view. So if I was to go into
source files, for example, and add a new
item, source files is in a folder. So,
if I add an item or something called
main.cpp, once it creates the file and
everything, you'll see that it's
actually just created that right here
next to my project. And that's just I
just that's just that's just messy,
right? What like what why? So, what I
like to do is I like to create a folder
called source or src, which contains all
of my source code and header files and
all that stuff kind of in that folder so
that my project files and any other
resources that I might be using in my
project are actually kind of nicely
separated into folders. And that's
something that that Visual Studio
doesn't set up for you automatically. So
you kind of have to roll with it. So if
we go back to Visual Studio, we can
click on our project here and a little
button will appear here which says show
all files. If we click that this view,
this view is actually your directory
structure that is on your disk that is
on your hard drive. So if I right click
now and hit add, you'll see the filter
is replaced with new folder and I can
actually make a folder called src.
Right? If I alt tab back to my file
explorer, look at that. We've got a
folder called source. So, let's move
this main.cpp file into that source
directory. Now, I can do so using
Windows Explorer, which would mean that
I would have to manually update it in
Visual Studio. Or I can just click and
drag it like that. And you can see that
on disk, it's actually moved it into
that directory. Okay. So, now Visual
Studio is actually behaving a little bit
more like I would like it to. So, this
kind of show all files button is
incredibly useful and honestly, I kind
of use that mostly. If we go back to our
filters, you can see that main is still
inside the source files. This is just a
virtual organization kind of scheme,
right? I can drag this to header files.
It doesn't matter where this is, right?
It could be just in no filters, which
would mean it's here. I can just go
ahead and delete all of these. In fact,
it doesn't really matter. These this
filter view is all just it's all fake,
right? It's all just kind of there for
you to just organize things into groups.
It has no no relation to actual
directory structure on disk. So, if I go
back to show all files mode, there is my
main.cpp file and I can do all of my
code here. Let's go ahead and just write
a quick hello world program. Just
something for us to build. All right.
Now, I'm going to compile this. So, I'll
right click on my project, hit build,
and you can see that everything will
build successfully. So, where has Visual
Studio put our .exe file? If we look at
the output, you can see it's gone to new
project, then debug, then new
project.exe. So, debug being our
currently selected configuration. If we
open our file explorer once again and we
check this out. So it hasn't actually
you can see there's a debug folder here
which is in the same directory as our
VCS project file. However, if we open
it, I don't see no no new project.exe in
here, right? So what's going on here? If
we read this a bit more closely, looks
like it's just new project then debug.
So it's not in that project folder. Huh.
Interesting. So let's go back to new
project and then go back again and then
debug and then oh it's in here. How
strange. Visual Studio. So, what's
actually happened is it's put our
intermediate files into a folder called
debug in our project directory and our
actual final executable binary into a
folder called debug in our solution
directory. I don't know who makes this
stuff up. It's really quite annoying. I
have not actually met any professional
developer who leaves these settings.
Everyone changes them because they just
honestly they are weird. Now, it's not a
really big problem to change these and
you can create templates and stuff like
that. So, I'm not roasting Microsoft too
much for deciding to do this. I'm just
saying that it's a little bit weird and
especially for people kind of starting
out who might not know that you can
change this. It's it could actually be
quite difficult to find your damn
executable binary once you've built it.
So anyway, so if we go back to Visual
Studio, if we right click on our project
and hit properties, you'll see that
under active under our active
configuration and platform, we have an
output directory and we have an
intermediate directory. So that's
actually where everything's going. So
you can see that everything that we
write here, by the way, is going to be
relative to the project file. So if I
put something like intermediates here,
it's going to be relative to that
project file. So in the same directory
as our project file which is this VCX
project file it will actually make a
folder called intermediates in this case
and put them all there. Okay. So what I
like to change this to now first of all
I like to go to all configurations so
that I'm editing all configurations. I'm
not going to make any any I'm not going
to save any of these changes that I made
here. Um even all platforms. Okay. And
then what I like to do is this for my
output directory. I like to put my
output directory in my solution
directory slashbin
slashplatform and then slash
configuration and then end that with a
slash as well. Okay, so what it's going
to do in our case is put this into the
solution directory which is the root of
this whole thing. What that means and
the reason I've actually chosen solution
directory is because if we have multiple
projects, right, for example, we build
DLL files or something that are needed
by our main application, we want them
all to be in the same folder, right? I
don't want to have to go into every
project's folder and then deal with
that. I just want all of my built
binaries in one place because that's
usually the typical case. You want them
all there. So, they're going to be in my
solution directory in a folder called
bin, which stands for binaries, in the
appropriate platform folder. So in our
case really it'll only be win32 or x64
and then inside a configuration. So
either debug or release in our case. Now
this last part putting it into a
separate folder for each configuration.
Again not something that I do all the
time. Sometimes I just like to change
the target name to maybe have debug
appended to it for the debug build and
potentially release or nothing at all
appended to it for the release build.
It's it varies honestly based on how I
how I deal with my projects, but in this
case, I'm just going to put them into a
separate folder. Now, intermediate
directories are going to be very
similar. I'm going to put I'm going to
I'm just going to copy everything from
the output directory, put it into the
intermediate directory. The only
difference is that inside bin, I'm going
to make a folder called intermediates
and then put them there by platform, by
configuration. Again, sometimes I put
this intermediates folder at the very
end so that it's already inside
everything. But this way, it's just a
little bit cleaner for you to be able to
copy, say, the platform that you want
and only have all the built binaries, no
intermediate files. So, if I now hit
okay, right, we can clean our project,
which should get rid of a lot of the
previous files. If not, cuz it never
really does work that well. I like to go
into the file explorer and just delete
all of these files that I don't care
about. So, all the debug directory. You
can see that now I'll even delete this
bin directory. You can see that now all
we have is a solution file, the project,
we've got the project filters and a user
file which is just basically our current
Visual Studio configuration. And then in
source we've got main. So it's nice and
clean. I'm going to go back to Visual
Studio and I'm going to build. All
right, cool. So if we go back here and
we go to bin, we can see we've got
intermediates and then Win32. So inside
intermediates, we've got Win32 debug.
That's all of our intermediate files
such as our OBJ files. And then if we go
back, you can see we've got win32 debug
and then that is our exe file and we can
run that and everything's fine. All
right, cool. One little thing as well.
You can see that we've got a double
backslash here because of course I did
forget that the solution directory,
anything that has like project directory
or solution directory actually has a
backslash on it already because it's a
directory name. So we can just go back
and fix that up so that we don't get the
double backslash. If you're not sure
what one of these macros is equal to or
you would like to see what it is, you
can just go under edit here and then we
can expand this macros view. And then
over here we've got everything we want.
So for example, that solution directory
that I was talking about, you can see
it's cdev new project. And you can see
it does in fact end with a backslash.
All right, cool. So that's pretty much
it. That's all I just wanted to say.
Setting up your directories, really
important, really quick tip that that
will just kind of make your life easier
as far as organization goes. These are
the settings that I use all the time. We
might talk about more or less the
compiler settings and linking settings
and all of those kind of maybe release
mode optimization settings in another
video. I just wanted to show you guys
the basis of how I set up every new C++
project that I do. If you guys enjoy
this video, please hit that like button,
follow me on Twitter and
Instagram, and and I will see you guys
in the next video. Goodbye.
[Music]
Hey, hey,
hey, hey, hey.